The pianist was only pounding the keys
with spread-eagled fingers, chords only.
Chinese chords, they shuddered the piano
in every timber, chink and wire.
"Blowing!"
"Wow!" said Dean.
He was rubbing his chest and belly.
His t-shirt was out.
The sweat splashed from his face.
"Blow, man, blow!"
The beheaded tenor man was blowing at the
peak of a wonderfully
satisfactory free idea.
"Everybody was rocking and roaring.
Our girls, Galatea and Alice, with beers
in their hands, were
standing on the chairs,
shaking and jumping.
Groups of colored studs stumbled in from
the street, falling over one another.
"Get there!
Stay with it, man!"
Roared a man with a fog horned voice and
let out a big groan
that would have been heard
clear to sacramental.
"Boom!
Kick!" That drummer was kicking his drums down
the cellar and rolling
the beat upstairs with
his murderous sticks of rattly boom.
"Crash!"
Rattledy boom!
Uproars of music.
Big fat man was jumping on the platform
making it sag and freak.
And the tenor man had it, and everybody
knew he had it, a
rising and falling rift that
went from "Eeee-ya!" to a crazier
"Eeee-ya!" and blasted
along to the rolling crash of
buttscared drums hammered by a big,
brutal-looking girl-sconce
guy with a bow-neck who didn't
give a damn about
anything but punishing his tubs.
Dean was clutching his head in the crowd,
and it was a mad cloud.
They were all urging that tenor man to
hold it and keep it
with cries and wild eyes.
He was raising himself from a crouch and
going down again with
his horn, looping it
up in a clear cry above the furo.
A six-foot skinny woman was rolling her
bones with the man's horn
bell, and he just jabbed
it at her, playing "Eeee-eee-eee!"
He had a fog horn torn,
because the horn was taped.
He was a shipyard
worker, and he didn't do it.
When a tenor man jumped down from the
platform and just stood
buried in the crowd, blowing
around, his hat was over his eyes.
Somebody pushed it back for him.
He just hauled back and stamped his foot
and blew down a horse
bowing in glass and drew
breath and raised the horn high and blew
high wide and screaming in the air.
Dean was directly in front of him with
his face glued to the
bell of the horn, clapping
his hands, pouring
sweat on the man's keys.
When the man noticed and laughed at his
horn along quivering
crazy mules, hee-haw, and
everybody else laughed and they rocked.
And finally the tenor man decided to blow
his top and crouched down and squatted on
the floor and held a note in high sea for
a long time as
everything else crashed along
spittily boom and the cries increased,
and I thought the cops
would come swarming from
the nearest precinct.
The clock on the wall quivered and shook.
Nobody cared about that thing.
Dean was in the trance.
The tenor man's eyes were fixed straight
on him and he had
found a madman who not only
understood but cared and wanted to
understand more and
much more than there was.
And they began dueling for this.
Everything came out of the horn.
No more phrases, just cries, cries.